porcleain vs plumbing

=> Porcelain:
It is the interface, commands you type like git branch, git add, git commit

=> Plumbing:
It is the how git works under the hood

=> Why use commnd line?
- to fully understand what's going on under the hood, it is necessary to use command line becuase using GUI tools you can do things but you never get fully understanding what's going under the hood.

=> Git?
- It is a distributed version control system (DVS)

=> But how, git stores information?
- At its core, git is kind of like key-value stores
- value = data
- key   = hash of the data and use key to retrive the content
    - key is SHA1
        - a cryptographic hash function
        - produce 40 digits hexadecimal number from given data
        - will always be same if given input is same
    - So, when you "git log", see 40 digit hexadecimal no, those are SHA1s
    - Sometimes these types of systems are called "Content Addressable Storage Systems" becuase you can use content to generate a key

=> How git store things?
- git store things in objects
- the very basic object is called "Blob"
    - git store compressed data in a blog along with some metadata about that blog in header
    like word blob, size of content, \0 delimiter (null string terminator in C), content
- the way git does thing in a plumbing command is "git hash-object --stdin" of the string "echo 'Hello, World!'" [8ab686eafeb1f44702738c8b0f24f2567c36da6d]
- stdin means get the input from the terminal otherwise it expects intput from a file
[8ab686eafeb1f44702738c8b0f24f2567c36da6d]
- As, you can see the two hashes are same becuase the content is same
- the two pieces of content generates the same SHA are infinity small

=> Now, where does git store these objects?
- it stores it in .git directory (can be created by using "git init" command)

=> Where are the Blobs stored?
- go ahead and write that blog using "-w --stdin" flags like "echo 'Hello, World!' | git hash-object -w --stdin"

=> How to remote directory?
- using "rm -rf .git/hooks"

=> How to see files and directories in Tree structure form?
- use "tree .git" where .git is the name of directory which you want to see in a tree form

$ tree .git
.git
|-- HEAD
|-- config
|-- description
|-- info
|   `-- exclude
|-- objects
|   |-- 8a
|   |   `-- b686eafeb1f44702738c8b0f24f2567c36da6d
|   |-- info
|   `-- pack
`-- refs
    |-- heads
    `-- tags
8 directories, 5 files

- So, our blog is stored in the "objects" directory, directory starts with the first two characters of the hash like "8a" and the file is the rest of the characters like "b686eafeb1f44702738c8b0f24f2567c36da6d"


=> But, we need something else, That blog is missing some information like "filenames and directory structure"

=> So, if we save file as a blob then how do we know waht that file was called and what directory it was stored in?
- git stores that information in something called "tree"
    - tree contains pointers (using SHA1) to blobs and pointer to other trees and Why is that?
        - It's because subdirectories can be nested
    - tree also has some metadata like
        - type of pointer (blog or tree)
        - filename or directory of the thing that it is pointing to
        - mode (whether it is executable file, symbolic link, ...) and these things are important when you pull down the repo again. For example, if you are storing a script and that script is executable, the next person who goes and pulls down your repo will have an executable script, they don't have to change permissions or do anything special
    - tree points to other trees and blobs
    - they are directed graph

=> Note: Git doesn't store empty directories. The issue isn't with empty trees but it's a limitation in the stagging area. So, stagging area only keep track of files but not directories. So, we can't store empty directories.

=> In git, identical contents only stored once. And this is really really important that git implements and this is how git saves tons of space on your hard drive when storing full repositories. And the blog points to the same copy of (hash) and that's why checkig out branches in git is super fast becuase it only change pointer

=> Blob vs SHA1:
- SHA1: when you run hash object on a piece of content thats the number you get, its the key for the piece of content

- Blog: stores that key, that's how it knows which piece of content it's associated with

=> Other Optimizations- Packfiles, Deltas:
➤ Git objects are compressed
➤ As files change, their contents remain mostly similar.
➤ Git optimizes for this by compressing these files together, into a Packfile
➤ The Packfile stores the object, and “deltas”, or the differences between one version of the file and the next.
➤ Packfiles are generated when:
➤ you have too many objects, during gc, or during a push to a remote
- And, now you come to know that what "deltas" represents during "git push"

- git runs "garbage collector" under the hood to collect garbage data often after two weeks or on your specified time.



=> Git Commits:
- commits are other types of git objects that we talked about
- a commit points to:
    ➤ a tree (like root directory)
    ➤ and contains metadata:
        ➤ author and committer
        ➤ date (when commit created)
        ➤ message
        ➤ parent commit (one or more)
- the SHA1 of the commit is the hash of all this information

- commits point to parent Commits
- initial commit doesn't have any parent, its first
- second commits points to first commit as its parent (So GRAPH)
- So, commits points to tree and that tree point to other trees and commits and so on and so forth.

- tree is the snapsnot of repository.

=> of what the repository stagging area look like at the time of the commit?
- it points to those files and folders.

- So:
    - A COMMIT IS A CODE SNAPSHOT, what the project looked like at that point in time and it's a combination of the CHANGES from the stagging area on the previous commit.

- when we make commit, the first status line tells us:
    - what the hash of that commit is. Here hash starts with "adf"

- If we look in '.git/objects' by running "tree .git/objects", we see there is subdirectory "ad" with a new file in it.


==> Commits Under the Hood:
=>Now, what happends if we try to look at one these git objects of commit with "cat" command, For Example:
"cat .git/objects/98/0a0d5f19a64b4b30a87d4206aade58726b60e3
xKOR04fH/IQHak%", you will get nothing becuase these are binary objects, they are compressed

- So, if we want to look at them, use "-t" flag to print type of file and "-p" flag to print the contents of file

"git cat-file -t 980a0" => blob
"git cat-file -p 980a0" => "Hello, World!"


=> Note: We can't change commits, not even with rebase, we can't edits them, we can't go back and change the author becuase if you change any of data about the commit, it's gonna have a new SHA1. So, even if you copy everything else, you are gonna have new date when that commit is created meaning will have different SHA1 even if it has same contents.

=> Tags, Branches, HEAD:
- HEAD:
    - a special type of pointer in git
    - it points to current commit
    - when you checkout the branch, it points to the current branch
    - the very last commit that you made

=> Why is changing branches in Git lightining fast?
- becuase it's not pulling down new data, it just changing a pointer

=> References Under the Hood:
- there are two important places where References are stored:
    1. A file called "HEAD" (points to the current branch "master" and "intial commit" and master is pointing to inital commit)
    2. refs/heads directory where all your branches live



==> Setting up Default Editor on cmd:
Set which editor git should use.

This is the program that will open during a commit with no -m flag, a merge, a rebase, etc...

Select from any installed editor. Examples:

emacs: emacs
vi: vi or vim
atom: atom --wait
sublime: subl -n -w
vscode: code --wait
Run: $ $ git config --global core.editor <YOUR_EDITOR>


=> Tips for using less on the command line:

To navigate:
f = for next page
b = for previous page

To search:
/<query>
n = next match
p = previous match

To quit:
q = to quit

If you really want to deep dive, check out the man (a.k.a manual) page for less.

==> Execise 01: Commits
